Partial Inventory of the William Henry Baumer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Henry Baumer papers
1929-1991
91042
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (4.4 linear feet)
Diary, memoirs, correspondence, orders, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relating to Allied strategic planning during World War II, especially for the Normandy landings of 1944, wartime diplomacy and Allied conferences, and the Paris Peace Conference. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Baumer, William H. (William Henry), 1909-1989.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Biographical Note
Major general, United States Army; staff officer, War Department General Staff, Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Forces, and military missions to Great Britain and the Soviet Union, 1942-1945; military adviser, Paris Peace Conference, 1946.
Scope and Content of Collection
Diary, memoirs, correspondence, orders, memoranda, reports, and printed matter relating to Allied strategic planning during World War II, especially for the Normandy landings of 1944, wartime diplomacy and Allied conferences, and the Paris Peace Conference.
World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France--Normandy.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; United States. War Department. General Staff.; Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters.; Paris Peace Conference (1946: Paris, France).; United States. Army--Officers.
- Not yet described (Boxes 1-11)
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1940-1990
  Scope and Contents note
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some government records determined by the government to be unclassified. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2010 release of records, 1942 (Reading room workstation)
    - Memo to Albert C. Wedemeyer, "Request for Major William H. Baumer to Speak,", 1942 October 17
  - 2011 release of records, 1940-1990 (Box 10)
    - Baumer personal military file, 1940-1945 (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
      Orders, travel documents, and related material concerning Baumer's military service.
    - Important material for the book, 1944-1990 (Box-folder 10: 4-5)
      Letters, clippings, military discharge papers, notes, Baumer writings, memos, and other material.
    - Clippings, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - 2017 release of records, 1943-1977 (Reading room workstation)
    - Outline of AEFA Camp, CCS, and JCS meetings, 1943 January
    - W. H. Baumer letter to Lt. Colonel William J. Glasgow, 1943 May 29
    - William H. Baumer letter to Colonel Kahn, 1943 October 27
    - Movement orders to Lieutenant Colonel William H. Baumer, 1944 January 4
    - Telegram concerning Baumer's mission in Moscow, 1944 January 22
    - F. N. Roberts letter to W. H. Baumer, 1944 March 19
    - Release from permanent assignment to the Operations Division, War Department General Staff, and related documents, 1944 May
    - Movement orders to Lieutenant Colonel William H. Baumer, 1944 October 21
    - Notes from document on East-West relations, circa 1945
    - Notes concerning Operation "Switchback": "Clearing the Road to Antwerp,", circa 1945
    - Conduct of the war (1944-1945) and chronology of the war (1941-1944)
    - Orders to Colonel William H. Baumer, 1945 February 27
    - Orders to Colonel William H. Baumer, 1945 March 8
    - Notes on trip to Western Rhineland area, 1945 March 21-28
    - Orders to Colonel William H. Baumer, 1945 April 13
    - Agenda for conference with Soviet authorities regarding occupation of US Sector, Berlin, 1945 June 18
    - Outline: Changing relationships in Europe: Effect upon US military policy, 1968-77, circa 1977